{"tossups": [{"question": "This ruler defeated the Shardana pirates and captured the vassal state of Amurru and the port of Sumur before his campaign against Muwatalli II. This man commissioned his mortuary temple in Thebes and a pair of temples that were relocated in 1968 to accommodate the Aswan High Dam. This husband of Nefertari won the battle of Kadesh against the Hittites, the opponent of his father, Seti I. For 10 points, name this long-ruling New Kingdom Egyptian pharaoh who built Abu Simbel.", "answer": "<b><u>Ramesses the Great</u></b> [or <b><u>Ramesses II</u></b>; accept <b><u>Ramses</u></b> in place of Ramesses] [Bee]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A tribe in this region described as \u201ccurly haired\u201d were known as the Silures. Tacitus published a long history of a governor of this region who won the Battle of Mons Graupius. That man, Agricola, fought tribes in this region\u2019s area of Caledonia. A structure built in this region was  possibly meant to keep out the Picts and has \u201dbroad and \u201cnarrow\u201d portions. For 10 points, name  this province, the location of Hadrian\u2019s Wall.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>Britain</u></b> [or Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; or <b><u>Britannia</u></b>; accept <b><u>Wales</u></b> before \u201cCaledonia\u201d;  do not accept \u201cEngland\u201d or \u201cthe United Kingdom\u201d]  [Puma]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "After a series of competitions in this sport, two sides engaged in mutual popular boycott after controversy over the Adelaide leak and the bodyline tactic. That tactic neutralized the prowess of one of the greatest athletes to play this sport, Don Bradman, and was part of The Ashes series between England and Australia. This sport has Twenty20, One Day International, and Test varieties. For 10 points, name this sport popular in the British Commonwealth that uses a flat bat and wickets.", "answer": "<b><u>cricket</u> </b> [Patrick Lia<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In the Tummal inscription, this character and his son rebuild a sanctuary to the goddess Ninlil. In another appearance, he hears counsel about the fool being given chaff and about a three-ply rope not being easily broken. This character meets Siduri after mourning a friend for seven days and travels to see the flood survivor Utnapishtim. He defeats Humbaba in a cedar forest with the help of his companion, a former wild-man named Enkidu. For 10 points, name this king of Uruk, the hero of a namesake epic.", "answer": "<b><u>Gilgamesh</u></b> [or <b><u>Bilgames</u></b>]  [Doug Grae<u>bner]</u>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This Nobel Prize winning-scientist assisted Germany\u2019s production of chlorine gas and  oversaw its use at Second Ypres. This Jewish scientist\u2019s lab ironically developed the predecessor to Zyklon B. This is the alphabetically-latter of the two namesakes of a process utilizing Hess\u2019 Law to calculate lattice energies. While working for BASF, Carl Bosch refined a process named for this man. For 10 points, name this developer of the industrial process of ammonia production.", "answer": "Fritz <b><u>Haber</u> </b> [Max Schindler]", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "Its not Italy, but revanchists in this nation supported a cross-border raid called the Pork mutiny, and this nation\u2019s army would commonly surround troops in pockets called <em>motti</em>. One invasion of this nation attempted to split it in half by moving through Raate Road. A sniper  known as the White Death fought in one of this nation\u2019s wars, which began after troops attacked  the Mannerheim Line. For 10 points, name this nation that resisted a Soviet invasion in the Winter and Continuation Wars.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Finland</u></b> [or <b><u>Suomi</u></b>]  [Eric Mukherjee]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This organization implemented a free breakfast for children program along with community health clinics in attempts to expand outside of Oakland. The FBI infiltrated this group through the COINTELPRO program, and this group used open carry laws to counter police brutality. This group also resisted the draft by ambushing police. For 10 points, name this Maoist radical-left organization founded by Huey Newton and Bobby Seale.", "answer": "<b><u>Black Panther</u></b> Party for Self-Defense [or <b><u>BPP</u></b>]  [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This rebellion ended when Captain Thomas Grantham tricked its last group of fighters into  boarding his ship. The namesake of this rebellion denounced its opponent in the \u201cDeclaration of  the People\u201d and was replaced by John Ingram after he died of dysentery. This revolt\u2019s namesake member of the House of Burgesses briefly controlled most of Virginia. For 10 points, name this 1676 rebellion against Governor William Berkeley that led to the burning of Jamestown.", "answer": "<b><u>Bacon</u></b>\u2019s Rebellion  [Patrick Lia<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This movement led to the founding of the American Tract Society and involved meetings at Gasper River and Cane Ridge. Influential figures in this movement included Barton Stone and Lyman Beecher. Charles Finney described regions of New York influenced by this movement as \u201cburned-over districts.\u201d For 10 points, identify this period of religious revival which ultimately gave rise to the emergence of Baptism and Methodism, a movement lasting from the early to mid-nineteenth century.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Great Awakening</u></b> [prompt on partial answers such as <b><u>Great Awakening</u></b>] [Abid Hase<u>eb]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The oldest German one of these structures was reconstructed from the original stones in 1961. Many ancient forms of these buildings contain zodiac art, such as the one at Beth Alpha near Gilboa. All of these buildings contain a platform called a <em>bimah</em> or <em>tebah</em> for resting a certain text. Since 1970, many American ones have inserted optional <em>mechitza</em> walls to separate the sexes and all have an ark area that faces Jerusalem. For 10 points, name these buildings used for Jewish religious services.", "answer": "<b><u>synagogue</u></b>s [or <b><u>beth knesset</u></b>; or <b><u>beth t\u2019fila</u></b>; or <b><u>shul</u></b>; or <b><u>esnoga</u></b>; or <b><u>kahal</u></b>] [Douglas<u> Graebner]</u>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "In 1965 this institution was the site of LBJ's speech titled \"To Fulfill these Rights.\" Notable figures associated with this institution include sociologist E. Franklin Frazier and philosopher Alain Locke. Named for a Union General that served as Commissioner of the Freedmen's Bureau, its Metro stop is in the Shaw neighborhood. For 10 points, name this historically black university located in Washington, DC.", "answer": "<b><u>Howard</u></b> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this nation was removed in the People Power Revolution, also known as the Yellow Revolution, following the assassination of Benigno Aquino. General Wainwright surrendered this present day nation to the Japanese while besieged in Corregidor. For 10 points, name this country where American troops experienced the Bataan Death March.", "answer": "Republic of the <b><u>Philippines</u></b> or [Republika ng <b><u>Pilipinas</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The name of one of this man\u2019s works was inspired by a display at the Columbian Exposition in Chicago involving the lowering of the Liberty Bell. Another of his compositions was often used to accompany the two-step and was commissioned by its namesake newspaper, the <em>Washington Post</em>. For 10 points, name this composer of <em>The Stars and Stripes Forever</em> and many other marches.", "answer": "John Philip <b><u>Sousa</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This leader was sent to the Canary islands after the rise of the Popular Front and was a leader of the Foreign Legion during the Rif War. This leader is buried in the Valley of the Fallen, a monument which was built under his rule. This leader joined his Falange party to the Carlists. For 10 points, name this Fascist leader of Spain who won the Spanish Civil War.", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Franco</u></b> [or Francisco <b><u>Franco</u></b> Bahamonde]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Louisiana native Willie Francis sued E. L. Resweber to prevent this action, on the grounds that it had already been unsuccessfully applied to him. <em>Roper v. Simmons</em> placed age restrictions on this action. A set of 1976 cases that held that this action could never be mandatory, but overturned a moratorium on performing it, included <em>Gregg v. Georgia</em> and <em>Furman v. Georgia</em>.  For 10 points, identify this sentence often challenged as cruel and unusual punishment, historically carried out by electrocution or lethal injection.", "answer": "the <b><u>death penalty</u></b> [or <b><u>capital punishment</u></b>; accept specific answers before mentioned, eg \u201c<b><u>electrocution</u></b>\u201d before \u201celectrocution\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Salt water taffy was originally produced and sold in this city. Until his racketeering  conviction in 1941, Enoch \u201cNucky\u201d Johnson ran this city\u2019s political machine. This city's attractions have included Steel Pier, the first Miss America pageants, and a five mile long boardwalk. For 10 points, name this resort city, a gambling hub on the ocean coast of New Jersey.", "answer": "<b><u>Atlantic City</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, the Dinant Corporation owned by potato chip magnate Miguel Facusse\u2019 has been accused of aiding narcotraffickers. This country was expelled from the OAS after Roberto Micheletti became the head of this nation following the ouster of Manuel Zelaya in a 2009 coup. For 10 points, name this Central American nation, located just north of Nicaragua.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Honduras</u></b> [Republica de <b><u>Honduras</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "According to a book named after him, this god once spent eight years underground milking cows. This god turned Idunn into a nut to rescue her from her kidnapper Thiazzi. Skadi placed a serpent above this god, whose venom causes him to writhe so violently the earth shakes. This god took the form of a mare to sleep with Svadilfari, a union that produced Sleipnir. For 10 points, identify this trickster god of Norse mythology.", "answer": "<b><u>Loki</u> </b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In one of this artist\u2019s paintings, the title officer is supported by several soldiers under a</u></b> <b><u>wa</u><u>ving Union Jack during Battle of Jersey. George Augustus Eliott points toward several</u></b> <b><u>sinking Spanish soldiers in</u> </b><em><b><u>The Siege of</u></b></em> <b><u>(+)</u> </b><em><b><u>Gibraltar</u></b></em><b><u>, a work by this artist of</u> </b><em><b><u>The Death of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Major Peirson</u></b></em><b><u>. Another of his painting</u> shows a silver kettle in the hands of the (*) </b> silversmith Paul Revere. In his most famous painting, El Morro castle looms behind a harpooner saving a man from an anatomically incorrect marine creature. For 10 points, name this painter of <em>Watson and the Shark</em>.", "answer": "John Singleton <b><u>Copley</u> </b> [Aseem Keyal]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Duchy of Savoy was assured independence after this King\u2019s forces won at the Battle</u></b> <b><u>of</u> <u>St. Quentin. His signing of the Treaty of Joinville prompted another ruler to sign the</u></b> <b><u>Treaty of Nonsuch. A revolt against the forces of this ruler sparked the</u><u> (+) Eighty Year</u>s\u2019 War. This man\u2019s brother John of Austria won the Battle of (*) </b><u>Lepanto</u> during his reign. The Battle of Gravelines prevented this man\u2019s fleet from rendezvousing with the Duke of Parma and invading England. For 10 points, name this son of Charles V, the king of Spain who sent the Spanish Armada.", "answer": "<b><u>Philip II</u></b> of Spain [or <b><u>Felipe II</u></b>; accept variant pronunciations; prompt on <b><u>Philip</u></b> and <b><u>Felipe</u></b>]  <u>[Laure</u>nce Li]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of the first times this group flexed its political muscle was when it torpedoed A.T.</u></b>  <b><u>Stewart\u2019s nomination as Treasury Secretary. Prominent opponents of this faction included</u></b> <b><u>Carl Schurz and William Robertson. This group, which was led by Thomas Platt and</u></b> <b><u>Roscoe</u><u> (+) Conkling, was detested by the Half-Breeds and Mugwumps, and Charles</u> <u>Guitea</u>u proclaimed membership in this faction after shooting (*)</b> James Garfield. For 10 points, name this this group of pro-spoils system Republicans based in New York.", "answer": "<b><u>Stalwart</u></b>s  [Weiner]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Traditionally, this empire was founded in 802 AD after one of its rulers completed a</u></b> <b><u>cer</u><u>emony celebrating freedom from Javanese control. One ruler of this kingdom</u></b>  <b><u>conquered parts of the</u><u> (+) Malay Peninsula, but lost wars to the neighboring state</u>s of <u>Champa and Dai Viet.</u> That ruler, Suryavarman II, portrayed himself as Vishnu in a (*) </b>monumental temple complex that was completed after his death. For 10 points, name this empire that built Angkor Wat and lent its name to a 20th century Communist group in Cambodia.", "answer": "<b><u>Khmer</u></b> Empire [prompt on \u201c<b><u>Khmer Rouge</u></b>\u201d]  [Tejas Raje]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Nineteenth-century conflict in this country centered on the Bay of Plenty, which was the</u></b> <b><u>ho</u><u>me of an indigenous guerrilla leader named Te Kooti. Dusky Sound is an inlet of this</u></b> <b><u>country's southwest coast, which was a major early center of jade production. The</u><u> (+)</u> <u>Otago gold rush took place in this country, whose indigenous people call it by a na</u>me that means \u201cland of the long white cloud.\u201d The Treaty of (*) </b>Waitangi was a controversial land document in, for 10 points, what island country in the southwest Pacific whose capital is Wellington?", "answer": "<b><u>New Zealand</u></b> [or <b><u>Aotearoa</u></b>]  [Jeff Hoppe<u>s]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2007, this country's military dictator suspended the chief justice of its supreme court</u></b> <b><u>an</u><u>d declared a state of emergency before resigning the next year. This country's president</u></b> <b><u>Pervez</u><u> (+) Musharraf seized power in a coup in 1999 soon after the indecisive (+) Kargil</u> <u>War. I</u>n this country's most recent elections, cricketer Imran Khan's political party finished in second place. In this country's city of (*)</b> Rawalpindi, opposition leader Benazir Bhutto was assassinated in 2007. For 10 points, name this country where Osama bin Laden was killed.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of <b><u>Pakistan</u> </b> [Naveed Chowdhury]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man commissioned a thousand-page white paper intended to prove that the U.S.</u></b>  <b><u>had no hope of successful military intervention in China, which was perceived as an</u></b> <b><u>attempt to deflect criticism for \u201closing China\u201d to the Communists during his time as</u> (+) <u>Secretary. This man was accused of running a \"cowardly college of Communist (*)</u> </b>containment\" by Richard Nixon and of overseeing a spy-riddled State Department by Joseph McCarthy. For 10 points, name this much-maligned Secretary of State who served under the second Truman administration until 1953.", "answer": "Dean Gooderham <b><u>Acheson</u> </b> [Weiner]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The head of the losing commander at this battle was sent to Maroboduus, the king of the</u></b> <b><u>M</u><u>arcomanni. Segestes, the begrudging father-in-law of this battle\u2019s victor, tried to warn</u></b> <b><u>the losing commander prior to this battle, which mostly took place at</u><u> (+) Kalkriese Hill.</u> At <u>the subsequent Battle of the Weser River, Germanicus recovered a st</u>andard lost at this battle. After this battle, Augustus reportedly shouted</b> (*) \u201cVarus, give me back my legions!\u201d For 10 points, identify this 9 AD battle in which Arminius\u2019 Germanic forces successfully ambushed three Roman legions.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Teutoburg Forest</u></b> [or Battle of <b><u>Teutoburger Wald</u></b>; accept <b><u>Varian</u></b> <b><u>Disaster</u></b> before Varu<u>s is mentioned, pro</u>mpt afterwar<u>ds]</u>  <u>[Max Sc</u>hindler]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}